Charles E. Hatch Papers MS265
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Charles E. Hatch Papers
1916 -- 1977
circa 1920s -- 1940s
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
MS265
2.55 Linear Feet 2 legal size document boxes and 1 oversize box
Charles Elliott Hatch (1892-1976) was a Professor of Dental Anatomy and Operative Technic, Operative Dentistry, and Dental History at Tufts from 1916-1941 and 1949-1963. His papers document his teaching and scholarly activities, and include correspondence, reports, scholarly publications, photographs, awards, and certificates.
Good overall. Clippings brittle, some photos silvered.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Donald M. Nielsen, 2019, accession number MS-2019-090.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in one series. The order in which the material was received has been maintained.
Biographical / Historical
Charles Elliott Hatch (1892–1976) earned his Doctor of Dental Medicine from Tufts Dental School (1916). Hatch went on to serve as Instructor (1916–1921), Assistant Professor (1921–1925), and Professor (1925–1933) of Dental Anatomy and Operative Technic; Professor of Operative Dentistry (1933–1941); and Professor of Dental History (1949-1963) at Tufts.
Charles Elliott Hatch was born in Isleboro, Maine on November 17, 1892 to Alfred Porter Hatch and Sarah E. (Pendleton) Hatch. Upon graduating from Ilseboro High School (1911), Hatch attended Tufts Dental School, graduating in 1916. Hatch married Elise Turpyn December 20, 1919 in Cambridge, Massachusetts, with whom he had one daughter, Odette Eloise Hatch, born on July 29, 1928.
From 1918–1928, Hatch was a First Lieutenant in the Dental Reserve Corps. From 1941-1946, Hatch was a Professor and Chairman of the Illinois College of Dentistry. Hatch was Chief of Clinic at the Forsyth Dental Infirmary for Children from 1949-1958 and its Acting Director from 1955-1956. He received the Distinguished Service Award of the Tufts Alumni Association in 1956.
Hatch died in Plymouth, Massachusetts on October 24, 1976.
Content Description
The collection includes teaching materials, correspondence, speeches, photographs, writings, clippings, and ephemera documenting the career of Charles E. Hatch (1892-1976), Tufts Professor of Dental Anatomy and Operative Technic, Professor of Operative Dentistry, and Professor of Dental History. The collection also includes photographs of Howard Marjerison, Dean of the Illinois College of Dentistry from 1940 to 1943.
Tufts University. School of Dental Medicine -- History; Dental history; Teaching and learning
- Charles E. Hatch papers, 1916 -- 1976; MS265.000001
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Speech and presentation notes, circa 1916 -- 1976; MS265.000002; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Tufts Dental staff, circa 1940s; MS265.000003; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and biographical sketches of Charles E. Hatch, 1941 -- 1946; MS265.000004; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Dental journals and reports, 1929 -- 1962; MS265.000005; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Papers and speeches by Charles E. Hatch, circa 1929 -- 1940s; MS265.000006; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Speeches, articles, and memos by Charles E. Hatch, 1928 -- 1964; MS265.000007; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, awards, and Forsyth Dental Infirmary reports, 1941 -- 1977; MS265.000008; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photographs and awards, circa 1920s -- 1975; MS265.000009; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Howard Marjerison, circa 1940s -- 1955; MS265.000010; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Framed photograph of Howard Marjerison, circa 1940s -- 1955; MS265.000011; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Certificates and diplomas, circa 1916 -- 1950s; MS265.000012; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Certificates and diplomas, circa 1916 -- 1950s; MS265.000013 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Certificates and diplomas, 1916 -- 1919; MS265.000014; 1 Folder(s) (Box Large Map Case 3 Drawer 9)
  - Photograph of Howard Marjerison, circa 1940s -- 1955; MS265.000015; 1 Folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Photograph of Tufts Dental alumni reunion, 1926; MS265.000016; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 3)
  - Dr. C. E. Hatch nameplate, circa 1916 -- 1976; MS265.000017; 1 Artifact(s) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Signature stamp, circa 1916 -- 1976; MS265.000018; 1 Artifact(s) (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Charles E. Hatch at Alumni Association Distinguished Service Award event, circa 1950; MS265.000019 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes a note from Cecelia Van Auken of the Tufts Public Relations office.
- Photographs, slide, and postcard, circa 1954 -- 1956; MS265.000020 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Includes photographs and a slide of Charles E. Hatch at work in the Forsyth Dental Clinic and a postcard photograph of Hatch, his wife, Howard Marjerison, and others, possibly on a trip to France.
- Delta Sigma Delta photographs, circa 1915 -- 1916; MS265.000021 (Box Large Map Case 3 Drawer 9)
  Photographs include both Charles E. Hatch and Howard Marjerison.